<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learnig Py</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Machine Learnig Py</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</webMaster>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright by Machine Learning Py {year}, All Rights Reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>How to identify Anomalies/Outliers in Python</title>
        <link>/posts/outlier-anomaly-detection/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</author>
        <guid>/posts/outlier-anomaly-detection/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data objects or points which exhibit very different behavior than the expectations are called as &lt;strong&gt;outliers or anomalies&lt;/strong&gt;. They can indicate variability in the measurement, an error in the collection, a new point(due to some changes), or it could be true, which happens to be away from most of the observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detecting and treating outliers is an important part of data exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>Non-Negative Matrix Factorization(NMF) - With Examples in Python</title>
        <link>/posts/non-negative-matirx-factorization/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</author>
        <guid>/posts/non-negative-matirx-factorization/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Matrix Factorization&lt;/strong&gt;, aka NMF, is a widely used algorithm for the analysis of non-negative high dimensional data. The algorithm is handy in extracting meaningful features from a non-negative matrix. It was first introduced in 1994 by Paatero and Tapper. The algorithm has been long used for extracting information from chemical systems using data-driven approaches under the name * self-modeling curve resolution*. It got its name as Non-Negative Matrix Factorization after a popular article from Lee and Seung in 1999. The paper discussed &lt;em&gt;properties of the algorithm and published some simple and useful algorithms for two types of factorizations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-negative_matrix_factorization&#34;&gt;[&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;1&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>SMOTE for dealing with imbalanced dataset</title>
        <link>/notes/smote-dealing-imbalanced-data/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</author>
        <guid>/notes/smote-dealing-imbalanced-data/</guid>
        <description>It is generally not a good idea to train a Machine Learning algorithm when one of the class dominates the other. It is advisable to upsample the minority class or downsample the majority class. Synthetic Minority Over-sampling Technique (SMOTE) is one such algorithm that can be used to upsample the minority class.
When to use SMOTE Machine Learning algorithms find it challenging to learn the patterns if the examples from one of the classes are limited.</description>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>Scope of Variables</title>
        <link>/notes/variable-scoping/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</author>
        <guid>/notes/variable-scoping/</guid>
        <description>Scope in computer programming language means the visibility of variables. It is the scope that defines which part of the program can use/see the variable. In general, a variable, once defined, can be accessed from any part of the code. However, sometimes, we would like to restrict the use of the variable to a specific section of the code. Programmers may want to do this to avoid unexpected errors.
For example, you may like to limit the scope of a variable to a specific function.</description>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>A Step By Step Seaborn Tutorial</title>
        <link>/posts/seaborn-tutorial/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</author>
        <guid>/posts/seaborn-tutorial/</guid>
        <description>Introduction To Seaborn Seaborn is a python library which is built on top of matplotlib package. The package is also closely integrated with pandas data structure. Seaborn functions aim to make exploring and data understanding easy through visualization. The functions provided in seaborn can work on data frames and arrays. While building graphs the functions can internally perform statistical aggregations and generate informative graphs. In this article, we will leanr how to draw different types of charts using seaborn library in Python.</description>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>Python Programming Tutorial</title>
        <link>/posts/python-programming-tutorial/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</author>
        <guid>/posts/python-programming-tutorial/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; is a powerful and versatile programming language. It is easy to understand and learn. Today, the python programming language is widely used in the industry. Some of the applications of python programming include Web Development, Robotics, 3D CAD Applications, &lt;strong&gt;Data Analysis, Face Detection, Machine Learning, and Artificial Intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;. In this tutorial, we will cover all the fundamental building blocks of Python!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>About</title>
        <link>/about/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Will update soon (Mohit Sharma)</author>
        <guid>/about/</guid>
        <description>YOU DON’T HAVE TO BE GREAT TO START, BUT YOU HAVE TO START TO BE GREAT. –ZIG ZIGLAR
 Namaste 🙏,
Welcome to Machine Learning Blog - A place where you will find articles/tutorials related to machine learning(ML) with Python. The intention is to build an online resource that can serve as a knowledge base for aspiring learners.
My name is Mohit Sharma, a seasoned Data Scientist who specializes in advance analytics, machine learning, and deep learning algorithms.</description>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>